Guide to the AIDS/Brookyn Oral History Project collection 1993.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
AIDS/Brooklyn Oral History Project collection
Bulk, 1992
1988-1993
1993.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
46.79 gigabytes in 133 files, total running time: 34 hr., 2 min., 59 sec.; 2.5 linear feet in 6 boxes
This collection includes oral histories collected for the AIDS/Brooklyn exhibition, undertaken by the Brooklyn Historical Society in the early 1990s. The project attempted to document the impact of the AIDS epidemic on Brooklyn communities.
Historical Note
The human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), which can lead to acquired deficiency syndrome (AIDS), was thought to have begun in New York City’s gay communities in the early 1980s, due in part because of the large number of gay men who lost their lives during the 1980s and early 1990s to the illness. During this time, death was a common outcome. Over the same period, it came to be understood that the illness did not originate with homosexuals, nor was it only impacting them. In early 1992, Gay Men's Health Crisis reported that statewide, over 40,000 citizens had been diagnosed with AIDS. An additional 360,000 more had contracted HIV by that time, as estimated by New York State's Department of Health.
Brooklyn Historical Society began preparing the exhibition AIDS/Brooklyn in 1991. David M. Kahn, executive director of BHS at that time, had lost his lover Ron Wogaman to an AIDS-related illness earlier that year. With a goal of documenting the crisis in Brooklyn through the material culture, personal narratives and life histories of those living with HIV/AIDS, BHS opened the exhibition in April of 1993. The exhibition not only informed of the experience of people living with the virus, but told of the precipitating factors and collateral effects; the strain on their neighbors, friends and family members, practices and attitudes with regard to drug use and sex, prejudice and discrimination in communities, and activist responses. Until that time, only art exhibitions had been inspired by the calamity of HIV/AIDS. In the museum establishment, BHS was seen as having pushed the boundaries of what an AIDS exhibition could do.
Simultaneous with the exhibition, the borough of Brooklyn had an estimated 35,000 cases of HIV. There, as in the rest of the nation, the disease had disproportionately affected the African-American and Latino/a communities along with the gay community. Brooklyn, however, was experiencing demographic shifts in the spread of AIDS that differed from the considerable high-impact zone of Manhattan. The disease was impacting women and children in Kings County; over 1800 women were infected in 1992, according to the city's AIDS Surveillance Unit.
Nationwide, estimated deaths from AIDS peaked in 1995; over 50,000 U.S. residents died that year. Due primarily to multi-drug treatment and lowering infection rates, the number has declined ever since. However, due in part to minimal cultural awareness and dissemination of HIV/AIDS information in impacted communities, that decline has been uneven across different demographic groups.
Scope and Contents
The AIDS/Brooklyn Oral History Project collection includes oral histories conducted for an exhibition undertaken by the Brooklyn Historical Society in 1993. The project attempted to document the impact of the AIDS epidemic on Brooklyn communities. Recordings initially made on magnetic tape concerned the epidemic and were with narrators who had firsthand experience with the crisis in their communities, families and personal life. Narrators came from diverse backgrounds within Brooklyn and the New York metropolitan area and had unique experiences which connected them with HIV/AIDS. Substantive topics of hemophilia, sexual behavior, substance abuse, medical practice, social work, homelessness, activism, childhood, relationships and parenting run through at least one, and often several, of the oral histories in the collection.
Arrangement note
The AIDS/Brooklyn Oral History Project collection is organized into four series based on format.
• Series 1: Oral Histories consists of digitized oral history interview recordings. The series of oral histories was largely arranged alphabetically by the narrator's last name.
• Series 2: Oral History Transcripts includes transcripts of several interviews, also arranged alphabetically by narrator's last name. Interview abstracts are located in the "Summaries" folder in box 1.
• Series 3: Research Materials is made from what was gathered and generated through the oral history project and exhibition. The materials relate directly to the AIDS epidemic in Brooklyn, as well as to AIDS/HIV in the New York metropolitan area. This series includes magazines, books, pamphlets, articles, biographies, a radio program and resource lists. The research materials are located in three boxes and one binder.
• Series 4: Magnetic Tapes consists of oral history interview recordings on original videotape and audiotape recordings and duplicate audiotape recordings. The oral history tapes are labeled with narrator names and interview dates, and arranged in an arbitrary order in two boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers with varied restrictions according to narrator agreement. Oral histories can be accessed onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society’s Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Research materials are open to researchers upon request and are accessible onsite at the Othmer Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The oral histories that make up this collection were compiled by a team including a project director, researcher and a research assistant. Staff for this project included Dwandalyn Reece King (Chief Curator), Robert Rosenberg (Project Director and Interviewer), Robert Sember (Researcher and Interviewer), and Kathryn Pope (Research Assistant).
Related Archival Materials
In addition to this collection, Brooklyn Historical Society has one oral history recording also related to the AIDS crisis in Brooklyn:
• The Crown Heights History Project oral histories (1994.006) includes a 1993 interview with Dellon Wilson, a volunteer in the AIDS community.
For more information on this collection please visit our online finding aid portal.
Related collections located elsewhere include:
• The AIDS Activist Videotape Collection, 1985-2000 at the New York Public Library (MssCol 3622) includes an interview with Iris De La Cruz and a series of oral histories conducted by Gay Men's Health Crisis.
• The ACT UP Oral History Project videotapes, 2002-2008, at the New York Public Library (MssCol 6148)
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. Transcripts created prior to 2008 serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator’s speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Historical note bibliography
Highleyman, Liz. "New HIV Cases Decline in US, but Population and Geographic Disparities Persist." Aidsmap (London, England), December 8, 2015.
Kolata, Gina. "AIDS in San Francisco Hit Peak in '92, Officials Say." New York Times (New York, NY), February 16, 1994.
Kolata, Gina. "Targeting Urged in Attack on AIDS." New York Times (New York, NY), March 7, 1993.
Osmond, Dennis H. Epidemiology of HIV/AIDS in the United States San Francisco, CA: University of California HIV InSite, 2003.
Tabor, Mary B.W. "Chronicling the Spread of AIDS Throughout Brooklyn." New York Times (New York, NY), May 31, 1992.
Wong, Sumi. "Historical Society at Work On Show About a Very Contemporary Subject: the AIDS Epidemic and Its Impact on Brooklyn Residents." The Phoenix (Brooklyn, NY), September 25, 1992.
Young, Joyce. "Exhibit takes closer look at life with AIDS." New York Daily News (New York, NY), April 18, 1993.
ACT UP New York (Organization).; Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc.; AIDS (Disease) |z New York (State) |z New York; AIDS activists |z United States; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Exhibition records; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; HIV infections |z New York (State) |z New York; HIV-positive persons |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interviews (sound recordings); Oral histories (document genres); Self-help groups |z New York (State) |z New York; Sexual health |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social group work |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Stigma (Social psychology) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transcripts
- Series 1: Oral Histories, Bulk, 1992; 1992-1993
- Broman, Melinda, 1992 June 20; 1993.001.01
  Biographical/Historical note
  Melinda Broman, a White woman, was forty-seven years old when she was interviewed. Her husband Victor Ockey, who was a hemophiliac, died of acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS) in 1989. He was infected with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) during a routine blood transfusion in the early 1980s. At the time of this interview, Broman had lived in Brooklyn's Cobble Hill neighborhood since the mid-1980s. Broman's involvement with AIDS was extensive, reaching beyond her relationship with her husband. As a member of the National Hemophiliac Association she has lobbied for increased awareness of the specific plight of HIV+ hemophiliacs. Through her work as a psychologist at Downstate Medical Center and as a member of the Brooklyn Psychological Association she has organized AIDS workshops. She was interviewed primarily because of her personal and professional experience with AIDS issues specific to hemophiliacs.
  Scope and Contents
  In the interview, Melinda Broman was able to provide a lot of information about what it was to be a heterosexual woman within a straight relationship dealing with HIV/AIDS. She speaks about the lack of support within the AIDS movement and also the lack of support from the hemophiliac community. While Broman found herself often surrounded by gay men within the AIDS movement, she made friends but was not always getting the support she needed. It was different within the hemophiliac community. She felt that fear of HIV/AIDS made the virus an unwanted topic of discussion. Melinda also speaks about being in a serodiscordant couple, the feelings she had about that, and how it related to her dealing with her own non-HIV-related health issues. Interview conducted by Robert Sember.
  Conditions Governing Access and Use
  Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires the permission of BHS. For assistance, contact library@brooklynhistory.org.
  Brooklyn AIDS Task Force.; Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc.; Green-Wood Cemetery (New York, N.Y.).; National Hemophilia Foundation.; White, Ryan; AIDS (Disease) |x Patients |x Services for |z New York (State) |z New York; AIDS activists |z United States; Blood coagulation factors; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Funeral rites and ceremonies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hemophilia |z United States; Hemophiliacs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; HIV infections |z New York (State) |z New York; Immunological deficiency syndromes; Marriage customs and rites |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Coleman, Philip, 1992 June 13; 1993.001.02
  Philip Coleman was fifty-two at the time of the interview in 1992. A gay African-American person with AIDS (PWA), he was born in Harlem, New York, lived on the Upper West Side of Manhattan for many years and was living alone in the East Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn. Coleman was a member of Gay Men's Health Crisis (GMHC) and, before he became ill, he used to conduct sensitivity training for volunteers working with gay African-Americans. In 1992, he participated in a HIV positive support group for gay men in Brooklyn. Being gay was Coleman's primary identification. He had been ill for some time and had previously been hospitalized with respiratory and circulation ailments shortly before this interview.
  In the interview Phil Coleman provides a clear sense of the impact that AIDS has had on the black gay community and on his life. He speaks candidly about what love, sex and relationships have come to mean to him as a PWA. Based on the experiences he had in his support group, he was able to make a few general observations about gay PWAs living in Brooklyn. Coleman shares throughout the interview his thoughts and feelings rooted in the intersectional experience of being Black, gay and living with HIV. He applies his analysis to what was needed in terms of activism, and services, and how racism and homophobia play out in church, in community and elsewhere. Throughout the interview Coleman connects the work he does around his being a gay Black man living with HIV to issues such as ageism, the house music and ballroom dance scenes, and even overlapping activism as it related to Haiti. Interview conducted by Robert Sember.
  Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc.; Kings County Hospital (Kings County, N.Y.).; Methodist Episcopal Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; United States. Department of State.; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; AIDS (Disease) |z New York (State) |z New York; AIDS activists |z United States; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Gay culture |z New York (State) |z New York; Gays |x Social life and customs; HIV infections |z New York (State) |z New York; HIV-positive persons |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Paratransit services |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Rotter, Beverly and family of Iris De La Cruz, 1992 April 03; 1993.001.03; De La Cruz family
  Iris De La Cruz is the daughter of narrator Beverly Rotter, mother to Melissa De La Cruz and sister to Randy Rotter. Beverly was one of the founders of Iris House, a care facility for women living with HIV, where she was also on the board of directors. She also founded Mothers March Against AIDS. At the time of this 1992 interview, Melissa was working with Lifeforce, doing safer sex education. Randy, during this period, was self-employed. Beverly Rotter died in October, 2015.
  Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires the permission of BHS. For assistance, contact library@brooklynhistory.org.
  In the interview as a family, Beverly Rotter, Melissa De La Cruz and Randy Rotter discuss Iris De La Cruz (1954 - 1991) and the powerful mark she made on the world as an AIDS activist, sex worker activist, and writer. They talk about her life and work before HIV and after. Each one remarks in their own way about Iris’ humor, kindness and fierceness as an activist. Melissa talks about what it was to have Iris as her mother. Randy discusses what it was to bond with Iris through humor, and also his anger around her HIV infection. Beverly speaks frankly about being a caregiver and the work that it takes to advocate for someone. Each also speaks about their own understanding of HIV/AIDS before Iris seroconverted (when HIV antibodies are detected) and after. Continuing to do the work of railing against stigma and discrimination, at one point Beverly asserts that the interviewer’s line of questioning is inappropriate and lets him know she will not continue in that direction. Interview conducted by Robert Rosenberg.
  Cuomo, Mario Matthew; Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc.; NYU Langone Medical Center.; People with AIDS Coalition of New York.; AIDS (Disease) |z New York (State) |z New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); HIV-positive persons |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Prostitution |z New York (State) |z New York; Safe sex in AIDS prevention |z New York (State); Self-help groups |z New York (State) |z New York; Social group work |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Stigma (Social psychology) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women |x Social conditions |x Poetry; Women's health services |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Fernandes, Carney and Kristy, 1993 January 11; 1993.001.04
  At the time of the 1993 interview, Kristy Fernandes was a seven year old girl who had been diagnosed with AIDS two years prior. Carney Fernandes, her father, was at this time age fifty-five. An immigrant from Guyana, he had tested negative for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and had been caring for his daughter on his own since her mother's death in the late 1980s. An articulate girl and keenly aware of her situation, Kristy was able to keep up with her school work and had only minor limitations on her daily life. Her father was very knowledgeable about developments regarding AIDS at the time of the interview and was very active in her care. Upon learning of his daughter's HIV status he went back to school to become a nurse. They lived together in an apartment in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  In the interview the narrators discuss Kristy Fernandes’ HIV positive status and Carney Fernandes’ role as primary caregiver. Kristy talks about her friends, the care she has received, what she wants to be when she grows up, and disclosure at school. Carney talks about Kristy’s mother, his previous relationships, and how he has dealt with Kristy's health. Based on his experiences he has a clear idea of what work has to be done to better respond to HIV/AIDS. Carney is outspoken about AIDS issues and the community. He provides insight as a straight man of color not living with HIV who is profoundly impacted by the virus. Interview conducted by Robert Rosenberg.
  Housing Works, Inc..; Kings County Hospital (Kings County, N.Y.).; Wyckoff Heights Medical Center (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; AIDS (Disease) |z New York (State) |z New York; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; HIV-positive persons |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Hargrove, Jason, 1992 February 4; 1993.001.05
  In 1992, Jason Hargrove was a high school student and a part-time AIDS educator with Project Speakout on AIDS Facts and Education (S.A.F.E.), a program of Project Reach Youth (PRY) based in Brooklyn's Park Slope neighborhood. He was interviewed as a teenaged "activist" after asking PRY for suggestions for one of their high school educators. He worked two afternoons a week; going to high schools, churches, and youth groups, etc., with other teens to conduct workshops on AIDS awareness and safer sex practices. He had no prior personal experience with AIDS, making him distinctly different from most of the other people interviewed for the project. Hargrove went on to serve as director of Project S.A.F.E., circa 2006.
  In the interview, Jason Hargrove discusses HIV/AIDS via his experience as a teen peer educator through the Brooklyn-based organization Project Speakout on AIDS Facts and Education (S.A.F.E.), part of Project Reach Youth. He speaks frankly about his own ideas and judgments about people most impacted by the virus, as well as how proud he is of the level of AIDS awareness among Brooklyn youth. In the interview he mentions some urban myths that surround HIV and what he would like to see the community and the government doing in response to HIV. He also discusses how different members of his family respond to his work, including his brother who also works with Project S.A.F.E. Not living with HIV himself, and having only met relatively healthy people with the virus, Hargrove has a specific view on the epidemic. Interview conducted by Robert Rosenberg.
  Johnson, Earvin, 1959-; AIDS (Disease) |z New York (State) |z New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Safe sex in AIDS prevention |z New York (State); Youth |x Sexual behavior |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Henry, Christopher, 1992 October 2; 1993.001.06
  A gay African-American, Christopher Henry found that he was HIV positive four years before this interview. That discovery was weeks before his gay cousin died from AIDS. He moved from his family home in the Bronx into his cousin's house in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1991. Apart from attending support groups at Woodhull Hospital, Henry was not then involved with AIDS-related organizations or activities. Henry did not consider himself an activist per se, as he did not carry banners. Instead, Henry saw himself more as a public intellectual in the making, akin to a celebrity or "public official." He was close to family, had a sense of community, and was raised with a Christian foundation.
  In the interview, Christopher Henry speaks of AIDS in the interview from the position of a young urban gay man of color; conscious of the role race and ethnicity play in understanding the issues raised by the AIDS crisis. When addressing his personal experience with the virus, whether he is describing his mother's reaction to his status or presenting anecdotes from his interactions with his gay friends, he is particularly forceful and articulate. Henry provides insights into the views of people impacted by HIV in Brooklyn related to the systemic issues of HIV/AIDS. He speaks about HIV being created by the government as well as how the government's inaction impacts care. He talks about the ignorance he sees within his own Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. He also shares a point of view about the virus that brings together spirituality, gay rights, and race awareness. Interview conducted by Robert Sember.
  ACT UP New York (Organization).; Ashe, Arthur; Body Positive of New York.; Hudson, Rock, 1925-1985; King, Rodney, 1965-2012; Montefiore Medical Center.; Sharpton, Al; Woodhull Medical and Mental Health Center (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; AIDS (Disease) |z New York (State) |z New York; AIDS activists |z United States; AZT (Drug); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Fashion designers |z New York (State) |z New York; Hepatitus B; Self-help groups |z New York (State) |z New York; Social group work |z New York (State)
- John, Marilyn, 1992 June 23; 1993.001.07